Guide to the Seymour Alpert papers, 1946-1993 MS2008
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Seymour Alpert papers
1946-1993
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Alpert, Seymour
MS2008
3.25 Linear Feet 4 document boxes, 1 slim document box, 1 flat box
This collection contains papers, photographs, and artifacts related to Dr. Alpert's private life, as well as his service to the George Washington University. The bulk of the collection deals with his private life, including his activities relating to his service for Israel Bonds. A large part of the collection is composed on unorganized and often unidentified photographs from Dr. Alpert's private life, although the researcher will find some images related to GWU medical school. The collection also includes original bricks from the "Tin Tabernacle" and the medical school.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains papers, photographs, and artifacts related to Dr. Alpert's private life, as well as his service to the George Washington University. The bulk of the collection deals with his private life, including his activities relating to his service for Israel Bonds. A large part of the collection is composed on unorganized and often unidentified photographs from Dr. Alpert's private life, although the researcher will find some images related to GWU medical school. The collection also includes original bricks from the "Tin Tabernacle" and the medical school.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 2005. (Accession 2005.032)
Biographical / Historical
Seymour Alpert (1918-2008) was born in New York, New York. He graduated from Columbia University in 1939 and subsequently attended Long Island College of Medicine. After a stint in the U. S. Army where he was based at Walter Reed Hospital in Washington D. C., he joined the faculty of the George Washington University School of Medicine where he practiced anesthesiology and taught from 1948 to 1983. He also served as Vice President for Development at GWU from 1969 until his retirement in 1983. He was awarded an honorary doctorate of public service from the university in 1984.
In addition to his service to the George Washington University, Dr. Alpert was also involved in several philanthropic organizations and activities. He was a founder of Israel Bonds of Washington and held many leadership positions in the organization. He was also active in the Hebrew University in Jerusalem for more than fifty years, where there is now an established chair in his name. He died in 2008.
Medical care; Israel
- Academic Articles, Speeches, etc., 1949-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Ashdod-Eilat Canal, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- D. C. Medical and Manpower Act of 1970, 1974, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- George Washington University - Development, 1946-1981; 1962-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- George Washington University - General, 1974, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Hebrew University of Jerusalem, 1973, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Israel Bonds, 1973-1993 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Memorial Funds and Chairs, 1964-1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- New Resident Orientation, Dept. of Anesthiology handbook, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Personal Correspondence, 1973, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photo Album, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photo Album - Europe Trip, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photo Album - Israel Visit, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs [1/7], undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photographs [2/7], undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs [3/7], undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Photographs [4/7], undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photographs [5/7], undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Photographs [6/7], undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Photographs [7/7], undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Photographic Negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Oversize images, Undated (Flat box 7)
- Potomac River Power Squadron, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Scrapbook, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Scrapbook, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- G.W.U., The Tin Tabernacle, 1924-1976 [Brick] (Box 5, Item 1)
- Original Brick, George Washington University Medical School, 1825-1974 (Box 5, Item 2)
- The George Washington University Development Office gratefully acknowledges your contribution to... [Plaque], June 30, 1983 (Box 5, Item 3)
- Resolutions honoring Alpert, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Harmoni Kings recorded at SD Studios [Audio reel], 1966 October 23 (Flat box 6, Reel 1)
- Tape of Radio Program after AMA meeting in San Fransisco [Audio reel], 1964 July (Flat box 6, Reel 2)
- Dr. Ariel Hollinshead, Medical Woman of the Year for the U.S.A. 1975-1976 [Audio reel] (Flat box 6, Reel 3)
- 1978 Prime Minister's Conference, State of Israel Bonds [Paperweight] (Flat box 6, Item 1)
- Pen with note [Pen], 1974 September 19 (Flat box 6, Item 2)
- The George Washington Law Association, The George Washington University Special Service Award for Faculty and Staff of the George Washington University...[Plaque], June 14, 1983 (Flat box 6, Item 3)
- Columbia College Medal, undated (Flat box 6, Item 4)
- Columbia College Medal, undated (Flat box 6, Item 5)
- Columbia College Medal, undated (Flat box 6, Item 6)
- The Jacob Burns, Van Vleck Moot Court Award [Medal], undated (Flat box 6, Item 7)
- The General Alumni Association of The George Washington University...[Award] (Flat box 6, Item 8)
- At Play in Colonial Fields [Pamphlet], undated (Flat box 6, Item 9)
- Silent Auction [Sign], undated (Flat box 6, Item 10)
- Award of Merit, The George Washington University Medical Alumni Association, 1965 May 29 (Flat box 6, Item 11)
- School of Government and Business Administration, George Washington University... [Award], undated (Flat box 6, Item 12)
- The Joseph Ottenstein Award for 1964 (Flat box 6, Item 13)
- George Washington University, GW Associates for Progress, undated (Flat box 6, Item 14)
- George Washington University, GW Associates for Progess, 1972-1973 (Flat box 6, Item 15)
- Groundbreaking Ceremonies for the Eugene Meyer Pavilion of The George Washington University Hospital [Engraved Shovel Plate], May 11, 1964; This plate was attached to a shovel. Digital photos of the original shovel are available upon request. Ask staff for assistance. (Flat box 6, Item 16)